先取得你父亲的同意解除婚约
Gain your father's approval to dissolve your marriage,
再带着你湿漉漉的身子来找我
and find me as wet with desire as you now stand.
听说你有意娶我的爱女 我很高兴
News of your desires to his loving daughter lifts heart.
按计划拿掉累赘
Remove encumberance as discussed.
你要打掉亲骨肉
You'll see your child never born.
这是必要的牺牲
A necessary thing.
有个红色的小药瓶
It's a red vial.
我想让你把里面的东西换成苦草和水
I'd see its contents replaced with water and bitter herb.
您妻子的奴隶晚上偷偷摸摸地进去
Your wife's slave stealing through the night.
她手里拿的东西我很熟悉
In her hand, a thing familiar to me.
我知道这是什么
I know what I hold
也知道你要它做什么
and the intent it carries!
不要让他们今晚就倒在这里
Let these men not fall here tonight,
让他们去角斗场
but in the arena.
我们要去卡普亚的竞技场
We are for the arena in Capua.
有请甘尼克斯
I give you Gannicus!
我们终于在竞技场上见面了
We had last faced each other upon the sands
正如梅莉塔所害怕的
as Melitta always feared.
你跟她上床了吗
Did you lay with her?
奥诺玛默斯
Oenomaus.
我们要用一腔热血扫荡八方
We will cover this land in passion
直到罗马帝国灰飞烟灭
until Rome falls as a cinder, to scorch brow.
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus.
盖尤斯 我父亲呢
Gaius, where is my father?
救救我
Help me!
他死了 死于斯巴达克斯之手
He has fallen at the hands of Spartacus.
《斯巴达克斯：复仇》
《抉择》
他们活着回来了
They live!
快把药拿来
Get the Medicine!
给伤员包扎
Get cloth to tend wounds!
战果如何
What news?!
竞技场已被烧为灰烬
The arena is burned to fucking ground.
顺带着送了不少罗马人上西天
With many Romans among the ashes!
莱斯克斯呢
What of Rhaskos?
他死得很光荣
He fell as all men should.
手里拿着剑 杀到牺牲为止
With sword in hand and blood upon his thoughts.
你没受伤吧
You suffer no wound?
是诸神照顾我 小家伙
The gods favor me, little man.
你再这么叫我
Call me that again...
诸神就该惩罚你了
and they shall turn from you.
还有救吗
Can he be healed?
纳西尔只有一处伤
Nasir had but a single wound.
他的伤势恐怕无力回天
This man beyond what should warrant life.
他是奥诺玛默斯
His name is Oenomaus.
可不是寻常人
And he is more than common man.
但愿诸神也如此看重他吧
Let pray the gods hold him in equal esteem.
我是在做梦吗
Do I yet dream?
如果是梦 我情愿你长睡不起
If so, I would never have you wake...
整个竞技场开始坍塌
Then it began to collapse.
大火中的人像小孩子一样
They screamed and flailed like children
哭天喊地 六神无主
as the arena burned around them.
浓烟和死亡的味道
The scent of smoke and death
随风飘到了罗马的最中心
carried by the winds to the very heart of Rome!
别担心了
Lift troubled heart.
奥诺玛默斯铁骨钢筋
Oenomaus stands a titan.
一定能挺过来继续战斗
One that shall live to raise sword again.
与你并肩作战吗
To fight by your side?
只要他支持我们反抗罗马的志愿
If he chooses to take up cause against the Romans.
你们的志愿
Cause?
你以为你是天神下凡吗
You have cock to rival Jupiter himself.
你这一帮叛逃的奴隶
A few errant slaves amounts
根本就是乌合之众
to flies circling a bull's ass.
他是不是忘了竞技场砸到他头顶上的事
Did he miss the part where we pulled the arena down on his head?
罗马可比那几根破柱子结实多了
Rome is propped up by more than a few wooden beams.
如果你们的志愿是少活几年的话
If your cause is to see your lives cut short,
那你们离成功不远了
then you march towards certain victory.
既然你这么想 为什么还要选择帮我们
Why did you choose to aid us, if you believe such?
你搞错了 我是来还债的
You mistake choice for repayment of a debt.
我欠奥诺玛默斯一笔债
One owed to Oenomaus.
否则
Absent it,...
我根本不会在这儿跟你废话
we would not be breaking words.
他说的对
He is right.
我们搞错了
We were mistaken.
根本就不该相信他
To have placed faith in his intentions.
纳西尔也想过要我的命
Nasir once made attempt on my life,
但他现在值得我们信任
and yet now he stands trusted among us.
说不定甘尼克斯也能改变
Perhaps Gannicus can be swayed as well.
也许你在竞技场里就应该杀了他
Or perhaps you should have killed him in the arena.
罗马的证人证明遗产的内容为
The witnesses in Rome also attest the will grants
罗马的家族住所和卡普亚的宅邸
the family domicile in Rome and the villa here in Capua.
还有阿泰拉的葡萄园
In addition there is the vineyard in Atella,
庞贝山里的四十头羊
forty goats in the hills of Pompeii,
二十头牛
twenty head of cattle
那些牲口总共值多少钱
What is the worth of the livestock?
取决于买卖契约 大概值九千第纳尔
Nine thousand denarii, depending upon deal struck.
拿到市场上卖了
See them to market.
所得的钱用来悬赏
And post decree announcing reward of the coin
能提供斯巴达克斯线索的人
for knowledge leading to the capture of Spartacus.
恕我冒昧 民政官大人 按照法律规定
Forgive me, Praetor, but the law grants you no such authority
您无权处置这些财产
to part with these assets.
您只能监管阿比努斯元老的遗产
You are only to oversee Senator Albinius' holdings
直到他的继承人成年
until his heir comes of age.
只要让斯巴达克斯落网伏法
Laws must bend toward greater purpose,
法律也要酌情改变
if Spartacus is to pay for what he has done.
民政官大人
Praetor
你的这些废话
Prattling on serves only to inflict
不过是在伤口上撒盐
further wound on grieving heart.
抱歉
Apologies.
我们会永远铭记您的父亲
The memory of your father shall not soon fade.
整个共和国都哀悼他的逝去
All the Republic mourns his loss.
退下
Leave us.
究竟哪一样让你更伤心
What moves your tears most?
永远失去了父亲的疼爱
A father forever removed from loving embrace?
还是他再也不能开口
Or his tongue forever stilled,
同意解除我们的婚姻
before commanding to dissolve this marriage
好让你嫁给瓦里留斯
in favor of Varinius?
我犯下了天大的错误
I have made a grave mistake.
诸神才会如此惩罚我
And the gods have punished me
让我的父亲死于非命
by striking down my father.
这样还不够
It is not enough.
盖尤斯
Gaius
要不是你腹中的孩子
The only reason you have not joined
你早就去九泉下和你父亲团聚了
your father is the child that grows within you.
那是我的孩子 我的继承人
My child. My heir.
你要拿命保护他
Protect him with your life.
不然我就要你的命
Or see it forfeit.
按规矩 这几天还是要表现出哀悼的意思
We must keep appearance of mourning for the prescribed days.
但你不能因为伤心就什么都不顾了
I would not have the stench of grief slick upon you.
去洗干净
See yourself to a bath.
有什么情况
Give report.
又在竞技场里找到一百来具尸体
A hundred more bodies pulled from the arena.
废墟里还有这个东西
This was found at wreckage.
怎么就剩这么几个士兵了
Why do our numbers stand so few?
正从那不勒斯调更多人过来 天黑才能到
More have been recalled from Neapolis, to return by nightfall.
还有的已经不见了
Yet many have taken to the wind.
这些人是要背弃效忠罗马的誓言吗
They turn from their oath to Rome?
这里人心惶惶 我们的人也不例外
Fear and panic grip the region, and our men.
他们相信斯巴达克斯招来了众神之怒
Many believe that Spartacus unleashes the wrath of the gods.
毫无意义
A meaningless thing.
加强军力并非难事
Legions could return to swell rank.
但休想打败斯巴达克斯那帮人
Yet still fall to Spartacus and his men.
说来抱歉 马科斯死之前我曾警告过他
Apologies, but as I warned young Marcus before life fled,
角斗士绝对不是普通的奴隶
gladiators are far from common slaves.
你手下三名士兵打不过一个角斗士
Three of your men would not equal one so trained,
这种行为纯属找死
despite their eagerness to die.
住手
No.
你以前也是他们当中的一员吧
Did you not once stand amongst the brotherhood,
算个角斗士
upon the sands?
很久以前的事情
A lifetime ago.
那就展示一番
Then give lesson,...
让大家开开眼
prove boast.
这叙利亚人敢情是想尝尝苦头
The Syrian wants to taste his own blood.
来呀
Come on!
怎么不动 打呀
What's the matter? Come on!
开始
Begin.
来呀
Come on!
他们向来认为 我是角斗士当中最差劲的
And I was considered lowest among the brotherhood.
莫非我要照你的样子建立一支军队
Would that I had an army formed in your base image.
像我这样的人不难找
There are others that share my reflection.
他们貌似常人 其实是狂暴的野兽
Men in name only, a word masking truer nature of rabid animal.
眼下时局艰难
Such a force under my guidance
由我指挥这样的军队 肯定能成气候
could prove useful in these difficult times.
元老院肯定不能接受身份如此低贱的军队
The Senate would frown upon lowering standard into muck and shit.
正如他们不懂什么叫做不择手段
As they frown upon many things that ambitious men must embrace.
你要走了
You leave these walls?
是民政官的意思
At request of the praetor.
他的提携是我阿舒尔应得的
He blesses Ashur with well deserved favor.
他伤心欲绝的妻子怎么就突然失宠了呢
Would that he turn such grace toward grieving wife.
丧父之痛 确实难以承受
It is a hard thing, to have a father torn from breast.
我都不知道我父亲…
I never knew mine
葛雷博怎么知道伊莉西娅房里的松香草
How did Glaber come to know of the silphium in Ilithyia's chambers?
没准是诸神告诉他的
Perhaps the gods spoke to him.
你忘了你的地位
You forget your place.
不
No.
我保住了地位
I secure it.
没有我 你什么都保不住
You secure nothing without me,
低贱的叙利亚人
you fucking Syrian.
你要是再敢违抗我的命令…
Move against my commands again
谁还听你的狗屁命令
You command shit and piss.
我是葛雷博的手下了
I am Glaber's man now.
如果我告诉他你知道伊莉西娅
A word from me how you knew of his wife's intent
想打掉他亲生骨肉的事
to rob him of his unborn child...
或者送来奥诺玛默斯根本不关诸神的事
Or how the gods are nothing to do with delivering Oenomaus...
你现在还能活命
You yet draw breath
是因为我没有把这些秘密透露给民政官
because I have not whispered your secrets into the praetor's ear.
不 阿舒尔 阿舒尔
No, Ashur. Ashur.
只当是好心帮忙吧
Consider it a kindness.
我迟早会报答你的
One I shall see repaid...
疼吗
Does it hurt?
一点皮肉小伤而已
A few cuts and scrapes.
很快就能忘掉了
Soon faded from memory.
不是所有伤口都那么容易愈合
Would that all scars were so easily erased.
我倒没看到
I see no scars.
你真是不顾一切
You risked all.
可你救回来的女人只有曾经的影子
For pale shadow of the woman you once loved.
那我们就燃起火焰
Then let us ignite the sun.
用太阳的温暖驱散阴影
And strike darkness with its warmth.
不要
Stop!
妮维雅…
Naevia...
他们夺走了我的一切
They have taken everything from me...
甚至你轻抚我的感觉
Even your touch...
我听说了很多你在竞技场的传奇故事
I have heard tales of your victories in the arena.
很久以前的事了
Days long past.
米拉说你当时就在竞技场上
Mira tells you were just upon its sands.
代表罗马给他们行刑
Standing as executioner for the Romans.
我是为了兄弟
I stood for a brother.
希望他体面地死去
See him to an honorable death.
莱斯克斯呢
And Rhaskos?
他死的时候呢
Did he find the same?
你跟他有交情吗
The man held some meaning to you?
他给我地位
He elevated position.
我给他暖床
I gave comfort.
看来你们的交易是到头了
It appears that bargain has come to an end.
那就另找别人嘛
I would see another struck.
找一个比他更厉害的…
With a man of greater worth...
我在他们当中没有地位
I hold no position among these men.
也没这个兴趣
Nor do I seek it.
可你现在跟他们在一起
Yet you stand among them.
我只想跟老朋友讲两句话
I seek only words with an old friend.
仅此而已
Nothing more.
我们就在这里 维苏威的附近
We are here, in the shadow of Vesuvius.
在山顶安排一个人
A single man placed upon
周围数英里的情况就能尽收眼底
its crest would have clear view for many miles in all direction.
很容易观察罗马人的动向
A Roman advance easily spotted.
有上山的路吗
Is there a way to its peak?
只有一条路
A single path.
很窄 但是好走
Narrow, but easily tread.
别的地方全是岩石
The rest is sheer rock.
除非长翅膀 否则不能走
Impassable, absent wings.
我们挑三个人
We will choose three men,
有丰富的战斗经验
of years beyond the taking up of sword.
每人守一个岗哨
Each to command a separate watch.
到神庙来只有一条路
There's but one entrance to the temple.
罗马人很容易困住我们
The Romans could easily trap us inside.
我们脚底下有地道
Tunnels extend below our feet.
也许可以挖一条出去
Perhaps one can be dug beyond these walls.
如果打通了路 几个弓箭手
A few men with bows would give the Romans pause
就足以拖住罗马人一段时间
long enough to make use of it, if walkway were built.
你们有几个练过射箭
How many among you shoot with purpose?
竞技场很少有射箭的需要
There is not much call for arrows in the arena.
你们如今不是在竞技场战斗
You no longer fight upon the sands.
而且拿一棵该死的树可造不出刀剑
Nor can you forge a sword from a fucking tree.
那我们就用现有的材料造兵器
Then we will fashion weapons from what nature provides.
有经验的人可以指导用法
With practiced hand instructing in their use.
训练到死有什么用呢
We can train until the gods take us.
打杂的奴隶不可能成为角斗士
House slaves will never be gladiators,
而我们缺的正是能打仗的人
something we are in short supply of now.
我们需要战士
We need fighting men.
也许该重新考虑那不勒斯的计划了
Perhaps it is time to revisit plans towards Neapolis.
目标是运送战俘的奴隶商船
And its slaver ships from foreign wars.
你要攻打港口
You would attack the port?
就这么几个人
With so few men?
我们火烧竞技场的时候人更少
We brought the arena down with less.
带两个人和所有的钱
Take two men and what coin we have.
在那不勒斯买通了人 就知道商船何时靠岸
Weight palm in Neapolis to loosen tongue of ships soon to dock.
抱歉
Apologies.
我无意打扰你们的谈话
I did not intend to halt conversation.
除非那地图能当酒喝
Unless I can drink that,
否则我对它毫无兴趣
it holds no worth to me.
我只是想找酒喝
I seek only wine.
我们这儿没酒
We have none.
这是什么破烂地方啊
Then I truly am among the damned.
伺候你们两个
For both of you?
我是妓女 又不是傻子
I'm a whore. Not a fool.
能聊聊吗
I would have words.
聊你妈
Fuck your words.
我不是在跟你说话
It is not with you that I seek them.
我有个活儿想找你干
I have an offer to discuss.
刚好可以发挥你的特长
One suited to your particular talents...
抱歉
Apologies.
我以为这些天你要守孝
I did not think you would need the bath,
就不会来洗澡了
with days of mourning yet left.
我夫君命令我来洗 尽管有悖礼数
My husband commands it, despite tradition.
留下吧
Stay.
我想让你陪着我
I would have your company.
你的眼睛刚刚哭过
Your eyes betray recent tears.
这些事情压在心里太沉重了
Events weigh heavy on the heart.
真是让人心如刀绞
To the point of crushing it.
为什么诸神没有警告斯巴达克斯的袭击
Why did the gods not warn of Spartacus' attack?
或者是我父亲…
Or of my father's
诸神是在惩罚我吗
Do they punish me?
因为我打算除掉的小生命…
A life, for the one I had planned to take...
我们都要为自己的行为负责
We both carry the burden of our acts.
如果诸神要抛弃我们
If the gods have cast us adrift,
我们必须一起寻找出路
we must together discover the course
重新获得神明的庇佑
to return to the blessing of their shores.
瓦里留斯抛弃了我
Varinius has turned from me.
盖尤斯又…
Gaius...
恐怕诸神也不能消除他对我的恨意了
I fear not even the gods could sway his hatred of me now.
你要做出贤妻良母的样子
Resume appearance of loving wife.
顺他心意
Submit to his will...
总有一天他会对你回心转意
The day will come when he will lose sight of hateful intention.
即便是转瞬即逝的机会
A slip, however fleeting,
我们都要牢牢地把握住
that we shall take advantage of.
有段时间
There was a time
我做梦都想把你亲手掐死
when all I dreamt of was your throat beneath my hands.
现在你却是我活下去的希望
Now your breath is all that gives me life.
我永远不会离开你
I shall not be moved from your side.
直到我的亡夫召唤我与他相聚
Until my own husband calls me to the afterlife.
我见过你这样的眼神
I have seen that look.
我们还在巴蒂塔斯家时
It often fell upon me,
你就经常这么看着我
when we were yet beneath Batiatus' roof.
在我到巴蒂塔斯家之前
You knew Gannicus there,
你就认识甘尼克斯了
years before my arrival...
你觉得他是什么样的人
What is your opinion of the man?
他是冠军 就跟我们以前一样
He is a champion, as we once stood.
有他加盟再好不过了
A boon to your cause.
不过他对我们的行为表示怀疑
He has expressed doubts towards it.
我们都怀疑过
As have we all.
而你总有办法化解我们的疑虑
And yet you always find way to convince otherwise.
我们做到了不可能做到的事
We have done the impossible.
我们摧毁了卡普亚的竞技场
We have brought down the arena in Capua.
摧毁了一座罗马压榨奴隶的纪念碑
A monument of Rome built upon the backs of slaves.
我们在敌人的心脏上狠狠地插了一刀
We have struck a deep blow to the very heart of our enemy.
但是 他们人多势众
Yet their numbers are vast.
他们渴望肆无忌惮地粉碎自由的呼声
As vast as their desire to see freedom crushed beneath heel.
总有一天 或许很快
One day, perhaps soon,
他们就会反击
they will strike back.
我们往哪儿逃啊
How do we avoid them?
我不想再躲躲藏藏
I do not intend to.
能怎么办 是真的吗
How? Is that true?
如果我们终究要面对罗马人
If we are to face the might of Rome,
那就在这儿决战
I would do it here.
就在维苏威的背面
In the shadow of Vesuvius.
按我们的规则来打
Upon terms that we set.
谁都不要袖手旁观
No hand will stand idle.
我们必须针对未来的情况做足准备
We must prepare ourselves for what is to come.
什么情况啊
What is to come?
我们会遇到什么事情
What is to happen to us?
我们严重缺乏武器
Proper weapons are in short supply.
所以要利用木材和石头制作兵器 确保够用
Fashion what you can from wood and stone, util more can be secured.
同时继续挖掘地道
I would also see the tunnels
做好撤退的准备 这也是非常必要的
beneath our feet further dug towards escape, which we will need.
再一次审视你的内心
To set eyes again upon your heart.
我理解了为何你当初那么不顾一切
I understand now why a man would risk all for such a thing.
如果没有你和大家的帮助
If it were not for you and the others,
我早就死在竞技场了
I would have fallen in the arena.
这辈子再也无法一睹她的芳容
Never to gaze upon her face again in this life.
大恩大德我没齿难忘
It is a thing I will not forget.
继续磨练战斗技巧
continue to hone skill.
不过你骗我的事还没完
Nor the lie you told,
任由她在那种地方受苦受罪
that saw her stay in that place another fucking day.
她没事了
She is safe now.
别的事情都不重要了
All other things fall to unimportance.
你以为动动嘴皮 发生过的事就能改变吗
Do you think a few words can change all that has happened?
那你就比我想的还要傻了
You stand a larger fool than I thought.
比敌人的千军万马还要可怕
be more dangerous than a thousand men.
我道歉
Apologies.
是我做错了
The mistake was mine.
帮了你这个操蛋的高卢人
To offer comfort to a fucking Gaul.
你帮个屁
You offer shit!
理智点儿
Regain yourself!
克雷斯
Crixus!
我以为这事情过去了
I thought we had moved past this.
伤还没好
Wounds still linger.
我要去那不勒斯了
I move for Neapolis.
找来一帮比他强百倍的人
And thoughts of swelling rank with better men.
罗马人算什么啊
You need not fear the Romans.
你们都自相残杀起来了
Your own men make attempt to kill each other.
你们都知道该干什么了
You know what must be done.
赶快去干
See to it.
甘尼克斯
Gannicus.
我要和你聊聊
I would have words.
你要我去打仗
You would have me fight?
我是要你去打猎
I would have you hunt.
没人可以不劳而获
Everyone has been set to purpose.
我们负责给大家找肉吃
Ours is to provide meat.
你说欠奥诺玛默斯一笔债
You spoke of a debt to Oenomaus.
难道救他一命不够还清吗
Was saving his life not repayment enough?
那得由他来决定
That is for him to decide.
你是自由人
You are a free man.
你可以自己做主
Your decisions your own.
可你还是去了竞技场
As it was when you stood in the arena.
准备干掉自己的兄弟
To strike down your brothers.
你怎么下得了手
What moved your hand?
为了荣誉 你有吗
Honor, as you have it?
还是金钱的诱惑
Or the promise of coin?
别站着说话不腰疼
Never to be collected.
我只是在竞技场上没杀你
Because I chose not to kill you in the arena.
如今我的鲁迪斯 我的自由
And now my rudis, my freedom,
永远埋葬在瓦砾之下了
is forever buried beneath its rubble.
自由不是什么木棍
Freedom is not a stick of wood,
那就是赏给忠犬的骨头
to be presented as a bone to obedient dog.
自由是所有人应得的
It is a thing all men deserve.
我们是角斗士
We are gladiators.
我们应得的只有死亡
Deserving only death equal
就像被我们杀死的人一样
to the lives of we have taken.
对我来说不是这样
It was not always so for me.
我曾经在色雷斯自由地生活过
I lived free once, in the lands of Thrace.
有妻子 有子孙满堂的憧憬
With a wife, promise of children...
后来她怎么样了
What became of her?
巴蒂塔斯杀了她
Batiatus claimed her life.
于是我也杀了巴蒂塔斯
I took his in return.
所以现在公平了
Then you have balanced scale.
葛雷博将我们贬为奴隶
It was Glaber who condemned us to slavery.
只要他还活着 我就不会停止战斗
And I will not rest while he yet draws breath.
这就是你对抗罗马人的原因
This is the reason you provoke the Romans?
就因为你妻子的遭遇
For the memory of your woman?
是因为爱
For love.
这是最伟大的理由
The greatest cause of all.
所谓的爱 毁了多少血性的汉子
One that has dragged many a man to his ruin.
你把猎物都吓跑了
You have scared away the game.
我还是单干吧
I would fare better alone.
剑不要放下去
Keep fucking sword up!
放下去了 你的脑袋就掉了
Let it drop, and fall forever beside it!
再来
Again!
我可不希望你热死了
I would not have you expire from the heat.
谢谢
Gratitude.
我也不希望你跟艾力冈起争执
I would also not have you at Agron's throat.
照他的意思
If he had his way,
他肯定把你留在矿上不管了
he would have left you in the mines.
也许他是对的
Perhaps he was right.
不要这么说
Do not say such a thing.
经过昨晚的事 你难道没这样想过吗
You have not thought the same, after last night?
如果有这种想法
If such a thought threatened,
我就把它从脑袋里直接挖出来
I would rip it from fucking brain with bare hands.
唯一重要的事情是
All that matters is the woman I love
我爱的女人回到身边了
stands before me once again.
是吗
Does she?
也许只是行尸走肉
Or is it but faint spirit,
还有以前的记忆罢了
haunting the memory of her body?
你疯了吧
You have lost mind.
死了几百人
Hundreds dead.
毁了一个竞技场
An arena destroyed.
你就提出这么一个破方法
And this is what you offer?
让露迪雅去市集五体投地
Lucretia to prostrate herself in the market,
祈求诸神熄灭那些还在燃烧的火焰
begging the gods to piss out the flames that yet smolder?
抱歉 赛普修斯只是太激动了
Apologies, young Seppius is but moved by passionate heart.
诸神肯定已经注意到他不虔诚的信仰了
I'm sure the gods take notice, of his lack of faith.
在诸神面前 我们必须谦卑
We must humble ourselves before the gods,
才能重新获得他们的庇佑
in attempt to regain their favor.
举办仪式可以减轻民众的恐惧
Ritual will do much to ease the people's fears.
抓到斯巴达克斯的效果更好
Better assuaged by the capture of Spartacus.
我的手下扫荡城外
My men sweep the countryside,
正是迎合祈祷的实际行动
taking action in favor of prayer.
可都好几个月了 你还是一无所获
As they have for many months, to no result.
你的人不也一样吗
Yours have fared no better.
这倒是 我们不能合作
True. The only one who benefits
从中受益的只是我们共同的敌人
from our divide is the man who causes us injury.
结果我们都看到了
And most keenly felt.
我们深切地怀念你父亲的指导和协助
Your father's guidance and even hand is deeply missed.
他离开人世 这些责任也就随之到头了
His absence from this world has set it upon end.
当我们的堂兄塞克斯
Seppia fell to similar heart,
被斯巴达克斯杀死时
when our cousin Sextus was
赛皮娅也是一样的感觉
snatched from life by Spartacus.
蒙卡图死的时候 她又体验到这样的痛苦
And she relives the moment in Mercato's passing.
在她小的时候 蒙卡图就常来我们家
A family friend since she was yet a child.
我们失去了太多朋友
Too many have been lost.
我不希望再有贵族因此而死
I would see no more of note to follow.
我们抛开分歧吧
Let us set difference aside,
集中兵力 合二为一
join our men in common force.
一定能彻底击败斯巴达克斯及其走狗
One, which will overwhelm Spartacus and his murdering horde.
是啊 为了民众的安宁
Yes, for the good of the people!
全城都会赞颂你们两人
The city will praise you both,
我们的声音可以传到元老院的耳朵里
our voices carrying to the very steps of the Senate.
我需要跟瓦里留斯商量一下
I would need to consult with Varinius.
那家伙还没等竞技场完全坍塌
The very same man who galloped back to Rome
就已经屁滚尿流地逃回罗马了
while the stones of the arena were yet falling?
瓦里留斯只想摆脱麻烦
Varinius moves to distance himself
根本不管这里发生的事
from all that has happened here.
也不管你
Including you.
来握手吧
Take my hand,
我们的联盟是坚不可摧的
and with it see more lasting bond forged.
我会考虑你的提议
I will consider your proposal.
明天给你答复
To give answer tomorrow.
休息一晚上
A night's rest, ...
别人没办法 他可爱的妹妹也许行
Loving sister may sway a brother, where others fail.
到早上就能决定下来了
...mind to be certainly cleared by morning.
赛普修斯
Seppius,
我想邀请你妹妹来
I would extend invitation to your sister.
两颗受伤的心相互安慰
In hopes that we may find greater strength
也许可以获得一点力量
in the beating of two wounded hearts.
好主意
A thoughtful offer.
对女人来说 同是女人来安慰
There is no deeper solace for a woman,
效果是再好不过了
than in the bosom of her gender.
那应该会让她感到安慰
It would come as great comfort.
谢谢
Gratitude.
我会安排的
I will arrange visit.
你妻子的脑袋很灵活
Your wife speaks with swift thought.
这件事情赛皮娅和你们有同感
Seppia will take words to heart on the matter,
而赛普修斯更听得进去她的话
with Seppius to find them better received from her lips.
是啊
Yes.
你的邀请也许很有帮助
Your invitation may yet prove to be welcomed aid.
过来 我还有别的事情要跟你商量
Come. I would discuss other matters with you.
我不是告诉过你吗
Did I not tell you?
我们总有一天可以再爬起来
Together we will see ourselves freed from this abyss.
我连人影都没看见
I do not see the man.
你确定他还活着吗
You are certain he lives?
曾经有四个人跟他一起待在下面
There were four others held with him at the bottom.
他不太喜欢跟别人一起
He did not care for the company.
所以就在皮肉上刻了他们的印记
Their memory is carved into his flesh,
以前他杀了人都把印记刻在自己的身上
joining the marks of the other souls that he has taken.
你为什么要找这种怪物
What is it you seek of such a beast?
我找这个埃及人的原因不关你的事
What I seek of the Egyptian is none of your concern.
我奉民政官盖尤斯•克罗迪斯•葛雷博的命令
I come under the authority of Praetor Gaius Claudius Glaber.
是大人物
A noble title.
但是 除非民政官本人来
Yet absent the man himself,
否则我无权放人
I cannot break my charge.
当然了
Of course.
只要你不介意跟这些人在一起
If you do not mind waiting here with my men,
等我带他回来吧
until I return with him...?
今天的天气太热了
Well the day has been long and hot.
我去乘个凉 再喝点酒
I would have shade, and wine...
降降火气
to cool overheating concerns.
弃暗投明吧 朋友
Let us see you into the light, my friend.
为我们效力
And set hands to purpose...
左臂要保持稳定
You must keep your left arm steady,
一直拉至脸颊 呼吸 放箭
pull through to the cheek, take breath, and release.
试试吧
Make attempt.
一直拉至脸颊
Pull through to cheek...
深呼吸
Deep breath...
放箭
And release.
不要猛拉弓弦
Do not jerk from the string.
要从指间轻柔地滑出去
But let it gently slip from your fingers.
多加练习 你就能像女神戴安娜一样
With practice, you will be as the goddess Diana,
从远处杀敌
striking enemies from afar.
多纳
Donar!
我想跟你一起
I would accompany you.
我对射箭没兴趣
I hold no interest in the bow.
睡了一次你就指望咱俩永远不分开吗
We lay together once and you expect us to never be parted?
你以为我是他妈的高卢人啊
You mistake me for a fucking Gaul.
你现在又想跟着多纳了吗
You seek Donar's affection now?
我只想能找到一席之地
I seek only my place in this world.
这要靠你的双手去争取
Then seize it with your own hands.
而不是靠张开你的大腿
Not by the spreading of your legs.
两周内 这里会停靠一艘船
In two weeks time, a ship will dock here.
船上载满了被罗马人抓住的战士
Its hold laden with fighting men captured by the Romans.
如果我们几个乔装成商人
If a few of us dressed as merchants
就能在他们下船之前进去…
could gain entry, before they're unloaded...
这方法可行
Such a thing is possible.
你的努力没有白费
Your labors have born fruit.
也不全是好消息
Not all as sweet.
街头巷尾到处都是流言
News carries through the streets.
葛雷博悬赏九千第纳尔要你的人头
Glaber has raised the bounty on your head to 9000 denarii.
看来你一无所获 只抓住了罗马人的注意
It seems you have caught nothing but Rome's attention.
这玩意儿可不太好吃
You will find that a sour meal.
高卢人还他妈的不够坏吗
Were the Gauls not fucking bad enough?
我听说了很多传说 说你是不败的高卢人
I have heard many tales of the Undefeated Gaul.
称号不错
A fine title.
我想起了那次你没获胜
Yet I recall you absent victory
那场我们跟索罗尼斯的人在竞技场的开幕战
when we faced Solonius' men in the opening of the arena.
是啊
True.
那时我没有获胜
I was not awarded victory.
不过正式的挑战赛中也没失败过
Yet I did not suffer defeat in proper challenge.
也许我们很快就要失败了
Perhaps we will yet have one.
也许吧
Perhaps.
听说你当过冠军 我很高兴
It warms heart to know that you were champion.
说明你很渴望冠军的称谓
Show how much you desired it.
不过在这儿看到你 实在是出乎意料
Yet it comes as a surprise, to see you here.
跟着那个色雷斯人
Following a Thracian's lead.
斯巴达克斯开了我的眼界
Spartacus has opened my eyes.
我们同生共死
We stand together.
那你怎么还坐在这儿
Then why do you now sit,
任凭他跟那个呆子商量行动计划呢
while he and the lumbering oaf make plans that affect all?
我有别的事情要想
I am taken by other concerns.
妮维雅是你的女人了吗
Naevia is your woman now?
我记得她那时还是含苞待放的姑娘
I remember her, when she was yet a flower untouched.
她怎么受到了那么严重的摧残
What led her to be so rudely handled?
我对她的爱
My affections.
还有发现了秘密的露迪雅
And discovery of them by Lucretia.
我们所爱的人总是付出最沉重的代价
The heaviest price is always paid by those we love.
你应该带她远离斯巴达克斯
You should carry her far from Spartacus
别跟着他搅和
and his foolish cause.
他迟早带你们走到绝路
Before he drags you all to your end.
奥诺玛默斯醒了
Oenomaus awakes.
我只是想跟你说两句
I am here only for words.
现在说什么还有意义吗
Which do you think could ever hold meaning now?
梅莉塔选择了你
That Melitta chose you.
所有人当中她最珍视你
That your heart was cherished above all others.
那为什么她死的那天你和她在一起
Then why was she with you the night she died?
为了在我被卖给图利乌斯前喝最后一杯酒
To share a final drink before I was to be sold to Tullius.
只有这个原因
The only reason?
无论我们发生了什么 责任在我
Whatever happened between us, I am to blame.
而不是她
Not her.
绝不是她
Never her.
我当你是亲兄弟
I loved you as a brother.
我也是
And I you.
不对
No.
你是一个自私自利的人
You are a man that stands only for himself.
为了满足你的欲望
And would betray the gods
你连诸神也能背叛
to gain what he desires.
也许我那时太傻了
Perhaps I was a fool.
信奉的是另外一套
To have ever believed otherwise.
我每次闭眼都能看到
I see it every time I close my eyes.
斯巴达克斯掷出的长矛
Spartacus, hurling his spear.
科萨特斯最后吐出一口气
Cossutius' final gasping breath...
还有蒙卡图
And Mercato...
可怜的蒙卡图
Poor Mercato...
我们都很想念他
He will be sorely missed.
很抱歉
Apologies.
我这样喋喋不休 就好像只有我失去过亲人
I babble on as if I am the only one that has suffered loss,
而你还在失去父亲的悲痛之中
and you grieve a father's passing.
我满脑子想的都是他
The heart is overwhelmed by his absence.
你们会重逢的
You shall embrace him again.
我和蒙卡图
As I shall Mercato,
还有堂兄塞克斯也是一样
and beloved cousin Sextus.
在往生世界的岸边
Upon the shores of the afterlife.
我的丈夫昆图斯还在耐心地等着我
Where my husband Quintus patiently awaits.
还有很多有身份有地位的罗马人
And with him countless other Romans of note.
我们共同的敌人就这样夺走了他们的性命
All snatched from this life too soon, by common foe.
你们两人都比我年长多了
The years between you far outweigh mine.
但别把我想得那么幼稚
Yet do not think me naive.
你不是为了寻求安慰而请我过来
You extend invitation not to counsel grief,
只是利用我说服我的哥哥罢了
but to maneuver me to sway my brother's position.
赛皮娅
Seppia
他的想法再清楚不过了
He's been clear in his desire that he,
他要单枪匹马制服我们共同的敌人
and he alone will bring our common foe to justice.
他这人下定决心就很难动摇了
And his passions when set are not easily moved.
你揭穿了两个老妇人的阴谋诡计
You have uncovered the veiled schemes of two old women.
但你要理解这种想法来自于受伤的心
But know attempt springs from wounded heart.
年龄和经验都无所谓 我们同病相怜是事实
One shared between us all, regardless of age or experience.
斯巴达克斯站在场上时 我看到了他的眼睛
I looked into his eyes, when Spartacus stood down upon the sands.
他眼中的怒火似乎要吞噬全世界
They burned with a fire that would consume the world.
毫无疑问
And it shall.
如果好人不能抛开分歧
If good men fail to set quarrel aside,
共同面对斯巴达克斯
and face Spartacus as one.
就像我跟你妻子说的一样
As I have said to your wife,
我哥哥是很难被说服的
my brother can be most difficult.
不是他一个人的错
Faults is not his alone.
很遗憾我没有选择更好的解决方式
I regret not having taken different path towards more agreeable solution.
但你要知道我现在是诚心诚意的
But know that I place foot firmly upon it now.
我自当进言
I will have words.
尽我所能让他站到你这边来
And attempt to set him upon it beside you.
多好的事儿啊 对吧 盖尤斯
Most welcomed news, is it not, Gaius?
没错 真是好极了
Yes, most welcomed.
近来这宅子阴云密布 有你在真是蓬荜生辉
You are a ray of light, in a house mired in shadow.
请原谅
Ah, forgive me.
有急事要办 恕我失陪
Pressing matters call my attention.
你真幸运 有这么好的男人
You're blessed, to hold such a man.
该是你的自然跑不掉
The gods grant only what is deserved.
你要的人都已经召集齐了
The men required have been assembled.
来吧
Come then.
我要看看他们有没有你说的那么厉害
I would see if they are all that you've promised.
甘尼克斯打来的猎物做好了
Gannicus' bounty is being prepared.
来吧 我们吃点东西
Come, let us take food.
你磨得好锋利
You have honed it to fine edge.
只要切开皮肉
Life would easily run from veins,
很容易就能死去
if brought to bear upon flesh.
妮维雅
Naevia...
这个名字已经没有意义了
That is a name that holds no meaning.
她曾经那么年轻
She was a different girl,
那么天真
young and foolish.
却让那些粗糙的手 粗重的喘息
Ripped from this world by rough hands
夺走了这一切
and hot breath upon neck.
为了活下去 她只能面对这一切
The things she was forced to do to survive...
我们离开这里
We will go from this place.
远走高飞 开始新的生活
Find a new life on distant shores.
远远地离开罗马的阴影
Beyond the shadow of Rome.
无论去哪里 都抹不去那些记忆
There is no place that memory would not follow.
我摆脱不掉
I cannot run from this.
你到底要我怎样做
What would you have me do?
眼睁睁地看着你憔悴至死
Stand idle, and watch as you fade?
不 我不要你这样看着我
No. I would not have you watch.
我要你教教我
I would have you teach.
如何获得新生
How to breathe again.
如何活命
How to live.
如何战斗
How to fight.
这样就再也没有人敢欺负我了
So that no man will ever lay hands on me against my will.
等到那时 我才能重新拥有那个名字
And the girl who's name was robbed may reclaim it.
我们一定要让恶贯满盈的罗马人付出代价
We will have vengeance for what the Romans have done.
我们一定要让他们血流成河
Together we shall see them drown in rivers of blood.
没有
Nothing!
不在这儿
Nor here!
保持镇定
Calm yourselves!
慌慌张张的干什么
What moves to such fits?
我们的钱全都不见了
Our remaining coin is missing.
钱算个屁
Fuck the coin.
地图不见了
The map is gone.
我们的方位 攻打那不勒斯的计划…
Our position, plans towards Neapolis...
有人为了拿到葛雷博的赏金 背叛了我们
Someone seeks to betray us, for promise of Glaber's reward.
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus...
甘尼克斯
Gannicus.
你一句话不说就要走了吗
You leave without words?
该说的我都跟奥诺玛默斯说了
I have had them with Oenomaus.
你身上带了什么东西
What do you carry with you?
水
Water.
还有肉 是我亲手打来的猎物
Meat, caught by my own fucking hands.
我们的地图不翼而飞了
Our map takes flight in your wake.
你当时看到过那个东西
A thing I have seen your gaze upon.
我是干过不少坏事
I am guilty of many things.
出卖你们的狗屁计划可不在其中
Betraying ill-fated cause does not stand among them.
你们还不给老子让路
Remove yourself from fucking path.
我早就知道你要带着他们送死
I knew eventually you would lead these men to their deaths eventually.
莫非你今天就等不及了
Is this the day you would do it?
他们都很忠诚
They are but loyal.
似乎正是你缺少的品质
A quality you seem unfamiliar with.
别过来
No!
不要挡在我们中间
Do not come between us!
我要让他瞧瞧 胸怀大志的人有多大本事
I would show him what a man with cause is capable of.
把剑给他
Your sword.
看来你是双剑角斗士
You fight in the style of Dimachaerus.
奥诺玛默斯亲自训练的
Trained by Oenomaus himself.
放我走
Let me pass.
否则就试试你的能耐
Or put skill to final test.
不能打下去了
We must stop this.
这是斯巴达克斯的愿望
Spartacus has made desire known.
我们要尊重
We shall honor it.
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus!
夏达娜
Chadara!
她想偷偷溜走
She was trying to slip away.
趁着大家都没有注意
When all others stood fixed.
好箭法
A fine shot.
我只想射伤她
I meant only to wound.
她偷了地图
She took the map.
她为什么要这样做
Why would she do such a thing?
她觉得在我们中间没有地位
She felt she had no place among us.
希望到别的地方寻求认可
She sought to secure one elsewhere.
抱歉
Apologies.
看来你说的是真话
Your words prove true.
不是次次都能证明
It has not always been so.
我要走了
I would take to path now,
除非你还要跟我打下去
unless you would seek further quarrel.
去吧
Go.
我们流的血够多了
Enough blood has spilled.
你不走吗
Do you stay?
不走
We do.
那我就等着为你哀悼了
Then I shall mourn your passing.
这样放走他行吗
Is it wise to let him go?
每个人都有权利作出选择
Every man has a right to his own choice.
甘尼克斯作出了他的选择
Gannicus has made his.
也许他是我们的隐患
And may yet prove a threat.
更坏的情况我们都经历过
We have faced far worse.
埃及人他们确实有些能耐
The Egyptian and your men prove themselves.
说到做到
As promised.
好好处理这些奴隶的尸体
See the bodies of the slaves properly attended.
不要惹人注意
Draw no attention.
抱歉
Apologies.
我不想等到早上
I could not wait until morning.
你要接受我的提议吗
You wish to give voice to my offer?
恐怕为时已晚
I fear it comes too late.
赛皮娅
S-S-Seppia...
我知道她对你有多么重要
I've seen how close you hold her to heart.
你就放心地走吧 她很安全
Leave this life knowing she's safe.
有我罩着呢
Beneath my roof.
到时候我亲手安慰她受伤的心
My hands to comfort her in days to come.
说什么都没有意义
Words no longer hold meaning.
我的耳朵早就起茧了
And I've had too many of them,
那些自以为高高在上的傻瓜废话太多
by fools presuming themselves to be my better.
这种日子到头了
Such days are at an end.
你的军队归我了
Your men are now mine.
有了他们的力量
And with their addition to my own,
斯巴达克斯的末日就要到了
clear path to the end of Spartacus.